

SOFTWARE ENGINEER · MI ENGINEER

➡ shubhamga2208@gmail.com | ★ www.shubhamg.in | ☑ goodhamgupta | ☐ shubhamgupta2208

### **Summary**

Software Engineer with eight years of experience in developing and delivering advanced solutions into many business aspects. Excellent ability to pick up relevant technologies for the task and implement end-to-end solutions to generate business value.

## Work Experience

**Temus** Singapore

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING MANAGER, DATA AND AI

Oct. 2022 - Present

- Implemented a financial assistant with LLMs and RAG, merging insights from structured and unstructured data via SQL AST parsing. Enhanced
  accuracy and relevance to 70%, reduced due diligence time by 20%, and cut inference costs by 40% with an on-premises LLM for structured
  queries.
- Implemented a Thai Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) system by integrating fine-tuned OpenAI Whisper with Voice Activity Detection and Speaker Diarization. Leveraged Llama for transcript correction, achieving a significant increase in intent detection accuracy from 11% to 17%.
- Developed LinguaForge, a multi-cloud platform using Kubernetes to manage batch jobs, train, and serve LLMs, reducing serving costs by 40%.
   Integrated SkyPilot, vLLM, and S-LoRA orchestrated LoRA Adapters for improved model performance.

**Aaqua** Singapore

APPLIED RESEARCH ENGINEER

Jun. 2021 - Sep. 2022

- Implemented a content-moderation system based on the OpenAI CLIP model to detect policy violating content on the platform, thereby decreasing manual moderation effort by 30%.
- Implemented a system to detect spam messages, based on the Microsoft MiniLM model and an open SMS spam dataset. The model was deployed using Sagemaker and FastAPI.
- Implemented a data platform to collect, transform and load data from multiple sources, using Airflow for orchestration and Datahub for data management.

RADICALi Singapore

SENIOR DATA SCIENTIST

Oct. 2019 - May. 2021

- Implemented an engine to identify similar documents and topics using LM Jelinek Mercer Smoothing, BERT and Query Re-ranking in Elastic-search achieving a silhouette score of 0.45.
- Implemented an unsupervised summarization model to find missing topics between two documents using GPT-2 and documents-as-graphs, leading to accuracy of 65%. Distilled and Quantized model to a LSTM leading to an increase in inference speed by 20x.
- Implemented multi-label risk classification for regulations using MultiFit, achieving an average recall of 87% across major classes. Deployed end-to-end pipeline using Flask, AWS Sagemaker achieving P95 inference time of under one second.
- Implemented a Knowledge graph to identify key topics and entities between upcoming legislations, helping users discover and visualize hidden relationships and build custom ontologies. Deployed system using Flask, Neo4J and Streamlit.
- Implemented a system to identify and cluster metadata such as Entities, Obligations using USE Embeddings, Flask and FAISS.
- Implemented a serverless scraping architecture using Scrapy, AWS Lambda, and Fargate scraping ability and increasing efficiency by 45%.

Scripbox Bangalore, India

PRODUCT ENGINEER AND DATA SCIENTIST

Oct. 2016 - Oct. 2019

- Implemented a hierarchical forecasting pipeline to predict the revenue and the number of customers in the future months using Prophet and Redash. Forecasts have been 93% accurate.
- Implemented a Hierarchical Bayesian CLV model using BG/NBD and Gamma-Gamma models which helped identify and segregate customers thereby increasing revenue by 10%.
- Developed a document processing pipeline using the YOLO DL model with OCR to help extract information from images thereby improving the customer on-boarding process by 50%.
- Implemented a real-time event sourcing pipeline using Snowplow, Kinesis, and Redshift which has helped improve customer and application
- Implemented near-real-time data pipeline to massage and aggregate data from multiple sources using Amazon EMR, Hive, HDFS and Airflow. This project is currently in the process of being open-sourced.
- Implemented the portfolio management platform from scratch which displays investments made, return percentages, etc. in Elixir thereby increasing performance by 10x.
- Implemented a data and analytics system to aggregate marketing campaigns spends and customer metrics from social platforms thereby helping reduce costs by 6%.

**Zopper** Bangalore, India

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Jan. 2016 - Oct. 2016

- Implemented a software database AESOP(LinkedIn) which helped process changes from one type of data store to another reliably. Ingested order processing efficiency by 13%.
- Implemented 'Catalog Extension' allowing retailers to source products from national distributors thereby increasing overall sales by 20%.

# **Selected Projects**

#### ExStan: Elixir <> Stan for Probabilistic Modeling

HTTPS://BIT.LY/EXSTAN

Lisbon, Portugal

Apr. 2024

Presented a talk on Probabilistic Programming using ExStan, Stan SDK in Elixir at ElixirConfEU 2024

#### **State Space Models for Language Modelling**

HTTPS://BIT.LY/MLSG-SSM

Singapore Feb. 2024

Presented State Space Models (SSMs), an alternative architecture for Language Modelling, in the ML Singapore Meetup

#### **End-to-End Attention based Image Captioning**

Singapore

HTTPS://BIT.LY/ATTENTION-IMAGE-CAPTIONING

Apr. 2021

• Implemented as part of a course project at NUS, and finished in top 10% of the leaderboard in the Kaggle contest.

#### **Open-Source Contributor**

Singapore

HTTPS://GITHUB.COM/GOODHAMGUPTA, HTTPS://BIT.LY/ELIXIR-PACKAGES

Aug. 2016 - Present

• Open source contributor to Nx, OpenMined and Snowplow Analytics. Packages have over **200k** downloads

• Presented research on Segmentation via Hierachical CLV at DeepBayes, Moscow, Russia in 2019.

## **Education**

#### **NUS(National University of Singapore)**

Singapore

Masters in Computer Science, Artificial Intelligence CGPA: 4.0/5.0

Aug. 2020 - Dec. 2022

### **Amrita School of Engineering**

Bangalore, India

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science CGPA: 7.96/10.0

Aug. 2012 - May. 2016